<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Declaration of the affections, intentions and resolutions of our brethren in Scotland for the peace and safety of both kingdomes. Whereby, the reader may observe how the present condition of this kingdome runs paralell [sic] with theirs then. God grant us now the like courage, affections, and resolutions, not to betray our King and Parliament, and therein, our religion, lawes, liberties, estates, lives, and the whole kingdome, vnder a blinde and false pretence of standing for the King, and so to betray all to the will of our perfidious enemies.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82114</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859133</idno>
  <idno type="VID">158230</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240868467</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing D626</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E238_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1179</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859133</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99859133e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82114)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 158230)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 41:E238[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Declaration of the affections, intentions and resolutions of our brethren in Scotland for the peace and safety of both kingdomes. Whereby, the reader may observe how the present condition of this kingdome runs paralell [sic] with theirs then. God grant us now the like courage, affections, and resolutions, not to betray our King and Parliament, and therein, our religion, lawes, liberties, estates, lives, and the whole kingdome, vnder a blinde and false pretence of standing for the King, and so to betray all to the will of our perfidious enemies.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>First printed in Scotland, and now reprinted at London for R. Harford in Queenes-Heal Alley.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Iune 20th. 1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-01 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:158230:1"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION Of the Affections, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions and Resolutions of our Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> for the Peace and Safety of both KINGDOMES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereby,</hi> The Reader may observe how the present <hi>Condition of this Kingdome runs Paralell with theirs then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God grant us now the like Courage, Affections and Resolutions, Not to betray our <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament,</hi> And therein, Our Religion, <hi>Lawes, Liberties, Estates, Lives,</hi> and the whole Kingdome, Vnder <hi>A Blinde and False Pretence of standing for the King,</hi> and so to betray all to the will of our perfidious Enemies.</p>
            <p>First printed in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and now reprinted at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>R. Harford</hi> in <hi>Queenes-Head</hi> Alley. <hi>Iune</hi> 20<seg rend="sup">th</seg>. 1642.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:158230:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:158230:2"/>
            <head>A Declaration of the Affections and Resolutions of the Kingdome of SCOTLAND, for the Peace and Safety of both Kingdomes.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE best endeavours and greatest works wherein the good hand and <hi>providence</hi> of <hi>God</hi> have been most evident and sensible, and the hearts and intentions of men cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to be the instruments, most <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>sincere.</hi> Though they found approbation with the <hi>wiser sort,</hi> and such as are given to <hi>observation;</hi> yet they have ever been subject to be misconstrued by blind <hi>suspition,</hi> to be reproved by cavelling censure, which maketh place for it selfe to enter where it findeth none, and to be condemned of the ignorant, and of such as are at ease; but most of all of the <hi>malicious,</hi> who cannot be pleased even when God is best pleased; and when men seeke to approve themselves to every ones Conscience, but in their hearts wish rather <hi>that the Temple should not be built, Religion never reformed, and they themselves</hi> Issachar <hi>like, couch between the two burthens,</hi> then that they should be in their worldly projects or possessions opposed or troubled: The <hi>deliverance</hi> of the people of <hi>God</hi> of old from the Aegyptian <hi>servitude;</hi> The <hi>redemption</hi> of the Kirk by the Son of God, and the planting of Christian Religion by his <hi>servants,</hi> and the vindication of Religion from Romish Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stition and Tyranny, which are the greatest and most <hi>wonderfull works</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> have been most bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly calumniated, and spitefully spurned against by the <hi>wicked.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The nature and quality of this <hi>good and great worke,</hi> wherein the Lord hath honoured us to be <hi>actors,</hi> and the experience which we have found of continuall opposition since the beginning, may teach us, if we be not <hi>as the Horse and Mule which have no understanding,</hi> that we are to expect the gainsaying of sinners, and that nothing can be hatched in Hell by Satan, or prompted by his Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posts on earth, which will not be produced to make us and the Cause of God which we maintaine odious to all men, but most of all to our Neighbours and dearest Brethren. When we shall now enter into <hi>England,</hi> it will be laid to our charge that we mind nothing but Invasion, and that no lesse hath been intended by us from the beginning, then under the pretext of seeking our Religion and Liberties to enrich our selves with their <hi>possessions</hi> and <hi>goods:</hi> But our peaceable carriage many yeares past before the time of those late <hi>troubles,</hi> our <hi>Informations, Declarations,</hi> and <hi>Remonstrances</hi> published to the world, wherein we have cursed all Nationall Invasion, and our willingnesse when we were in Armes to lay them downe upon the small hopes of enjoying our Religion and Liberties, and our forbearing now, by way of reprisall, to satisfie our selves upon the Ships and Goods of our deare Brethren of <hi>England,</hi> for those Ships and Goods of ours that have been taken by the Kings Ships, which possibly we might have been able to doe, had not Justice forbidden us to take from them, whom we are assured, neither with us <hi>harme,</hi> nor have done us <hi>wrong,</hi> will be conceived by the <hi>wise</hi> and well affected to be more plaine and sure evidences of our meaning then all that <hi>malice</hi> can devise, or <hi>calumnie</hi> can expresse against us.</p>
            <p>Neither have any new emergents altered, but rather confirmed our former <hi>resolutions:</hi> For although both before and since the late Pacification, we have been highly injured by some Papists and Prelates, and their adherents there, who have been, and are still seeking no lesse, then that we should no more be a Kirk or Nation, and therefore themselves cannot thinke but we must account of them as <hi>Gods</hi> enemies and ours: Yet above all the <hi>favours</hi> we have received from the good people and body of the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> One there is which hath highly honoured them before the world, and endeared them unto us more then before, which shall never be forgotten by us, and we hope shall be thankfully remembred by our Children, and Childrens Children after us to all <hi>generations;</hi> That when upon mis-information the Councell of <hi>England</hi> had concluded to raise Force against us, when the Parliament of <hi>Ireland</hi> had offered their Persons and Estates for supply against us; when all <hi>plots</hi> and <hi>policies</hi> were set on worke, and Publicke <hi>Declarations</hi> by Authority were made, and the <hi>Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament</hi> called for this very end, when we had been traduced, and proclaimed as Traytors and Rebels at
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:158230:3"/> every Parish Kirk, yet so <hi>wise,</hi> so <hi>grave,</hi> so <hi>just</hi> was that High Court of <hi>Parliament</hi> (to their ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting <hi>honour</hi> be it remembred,) that no <hi>threatenings</hi> nor <hi>feares</hi> no <hi>promises</hi> nor <hi>hopes,</hi> no <hi>fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse</hi> nor cunningly devised <hi>suggestion</hi> could move them to discerne a warre, or grant any Subsidie for a warre against us, but rather by their <hi>speeches, complaints</hi> and <hi>grievances</hi> paralell to ours, did justifie the Cause (so much as in them was) which we defend.</p>
            <p>This rich and recent <hi>savour</hi> doth so bind our hearts, that were our <hi>power</hi> never so great, we should judge our selves the unworthiest of all men, and could looke for no lesse then <hi>vengeance</hi> from the <hi>righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God,</hi> if we should move <hi>band</hi> or <hi>foot</hi> against that Nation so comfortably to us represented in that <hi>honourable meeting</hi> In this our <hi>thankfull acknowledgement,</hi> we desire that the City of <hi>London</hi> may have their owne large th<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re as they well deserve by the noble profession and proofs they have given of their constant affection to Religion, and the <hi>peace</hi> of both Kingdomes, notwithstanding the continuall assaults of the misleaders of the King against them, alwayes rendring them <hi>seditious</hi> in his eares. And if this which doth so convince us shall not be <hi>thought sufficient</hi> to <hi>satisfie</hi> all the good people of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> We now before <hi>God</hi> and the world make offer in generall, and we make offer to so many of them, as shall require it in particular, of the <hi>strongest</hi> and most <hi>inviolable bond</hi> of our <hi>solemne Oath</hi> and <hi>religious attestation of the great Name of GOD, who is our feare and dread, and from whom we hope for a blessing upon our expedition, that we intend no enmity or rapine, and shall take no mans goods, nor ingage our selves in bloud by fighting, unlesse we be forced unto it,</hi> which we may looke for from the Papists and Prelates, and others of that Faction: But that any such thing shall come from godly men, or good Patrons, who love the <hi>truth of Religion,</hi> or the Kings <hi>honour,</hi> and their owne <hi>liberty,</hi> both the rule of <hi>Charity</hi> (which entertaineth no suspition, where there is no evill deserving) and the rule of <hi>wisedome</hi> (which teacheth that both Nations must now <hi>stand</hi> or <hi>fall</hi> together) doe forbid us to appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend.</p>
            <p>All the designe of both Kingdomes is for the <hi>truth of Religion,</hi> and for the <hi>just liberty</hi> of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and all the devises and doings of the enemy are for the oppressing of both, that our Religion may be turned into Superstition and Atheisme, and our <hi>liberty</hi> into base <hi>servitude</hi> and <hi>bondage.</hi> To bring this to passe, they have certainly conceived that the blocking up of this Kingdome by Sea and Land, would prove a powerfull and infallible meanes: For, for either within a very short time shall we through want of <hi>trade,</hi> and spoyling of our goods be brought to such extreame <hi>poverty</hi> and <hi>confusion,</hi> that we shall miserably desire the <hi>conditions</hi> which we now despise, and decline, and be forced to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace their <hi>will</hi> for a Law, both in Kirk and policie, which will be a president for the like misery in <hi>England,</hi> who timously foreseeing it may be taught by their and our danger to be more <hi>wise,</hi> or upon the other part, we shall by this Invasion be constrained furiously and without <hi>Order</hi> to breake into <hi>England,</hi> which we beleeve s the most earnest desire of our common <hi>enemies,</hi> because a more speedy execution of their <hi>designe;</hi> for we doubt not but upon our comming clamours will be raised, Posts sent, and Proclamations made through the Kingdome, to slander our <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>just intentions</hi> (as if this had been our meaning from the beginning) to stir up all the English against us, that once being entred in bloud, they may with their owne Swords extirpate their owne Religion, lay a present <hi>foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation</hi> with their owne hands for building of <hi>Rome</hi> in the midst of them, and be made the Actors of their owne and our <hi>slavery</hi> to continue for ever.</p>
            <p>But in this admirable <hi>opportunity</hi> of <hi>vindication</hi> of <hi>true Religion</hi> and <hi>just liberty,</hi> if <hi>divine providence</hi> be looked upon with a <hi>reverend eye,</hi> and <hi>men fearing God,</hi> and loving the Kings <hi>honour,</hi> and <hi>peace</hi> of both Kingdomes, shall walke worthy of their profession, although the enemies have obtained so much of their desires, as by cords of their owne twisting, to draw us into <hi>England;</hi> yet may their maine designe be disappointed, the Rope which they have made brought upon their owne necks, and their wisedome turned to <hi>foolishnesse,</hi> which we have reason to hope for, from that supreme <hi>wisedome</hi> and <hi>power,</hi> which hath in all the proceedings of this worke turned their devises upon their owne pates that plotted them.</p>
            <p>In our <hi>Informations, Remonstrances,</hi> and the true representation of our Proceedings since the last <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification,</hi> we have so far expressed the wrongs which we have sustained, and the distresses which we suffer, as may make manifest our pressing necessity to take some other course for our present reliefe, then such <hi>petitions, supplications</hi> and <hi>commissions,</hi> as we have used before with lesse successe then could be expected of a Kingdome from their native King. Before we stirred so much as with a <hi>Petition,</hi> we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured for many yeares not onely the continuall opposition of the <hi>truth,</hi> and power of Religion by Prelates and Papists, but also the violation of all our <hi>liberties,</hi> and almost the totall subversion of our
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:158230:3"/> Religion, which was our comfort in the fight of God, and the glory of this Nation in the sight of other Churches, who by the testimony of their Divines made our Reformation the measure of their wishes, and would have redeemed it with their greatest worldly losses, when grosse Popery was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriously obtruded upon us in the Booke of Cannons and Common Prayer, without consent or know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Churches, and the plot of the Prelates and Papists wholly discovered how to settle it in both Nations We added to our former sufferings no other Armes but <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Teares</hi> unto <hi>God,</hi> and Petitions to our King, which were utterly rejected; the Books and corruptions against which we petitioned highly exalted, and by the insolent advise of those who governe now his Counsels, labour to establish their owne ill acquired greatnesse upon our oppression, and the ruines of our Religion and Liberties, we were forbidden to insist under the paine of high Treason.</p>
            <p>When we found our selves thus opposed and borne downe, still insisting in our humble desires, we so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely renewed our solemne and Nationall Oath and Covenant for preserving of our Religion and Liberties, and of his Majesties Authority, knowing the violation of that Oath to be the guiltinesse which had procured our woes, and that our Repentance and turning to <hi>God</hi> were the meanes by his blessing for a good successe, when contrary to our deserving and expectation his Majesty was moved by wicked Counsell to march towards us with an Army, we choosed rather to neglect such courses as might serve for our humane safety, then to fall in seeming disobedience to our King, or to give the smallest distaste to our Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> and therefore disbanded our Forces, delivered all holds which were craved in testimony of our obedience, and so farre complyed with his Majesties pleasure, that notwithstanding the determination of our lawfull former Assembly, called by his Majesty, we were contented that a new free Assembly and Parliament should be appointed, where all things both concerning our Religion and Liberties might againe be considered and established. When matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall were determined in the Assembly according to the Constitutions of the Church in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence, and with the consent of his Majesties Commissioner, and the Parliament was conveened for perfecting the warre, although we walked therein so warily, that no just provocation was given to his Majesty; yet contrary to the Lawes and Customes of this Kingdome, the Parliament so certainly promised, when his M jesty was free of those bad Counsellors, was (being againe in their power) by their advise prorogued, which to shew our invincible <hi>obedience</hi> we were content to suffer, and did send up our Commissioners to <hi>London</hi> to render the reasons of our demands. When our Commissioners and Petitions of the Parliament, called by his Majesty, were so farre rejected, that they were never seen or heard.</p>
            <p>We send up our Commissioners againe with our <hi>Propositions,</hi> which contained nothing but what was necessary for the <hi>peace</hi> and <hi>good</hi> of the Kingdome, and was granted to us before under his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties hand; yet could they finde no answer at all which will be wondred at, and hardly beleeved by so many as are strangers at Court, and know not the Bishop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the Lievtenant of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with the Assistance of the too too powerfull Faction of the Hispanioliz'd Papists labour to shew their zeale for his Majesties greatnesse, by oppressing the just liberties of the free Subjects, and the reformed Religion in all the three Kingdomes: But in place of the gracious answer which we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, our Commissioners were restrained, and one of the Noble-men imprisoned, Garrisons of strangers set over our heads in an insolent and barbarous way, exercising their cruelty even against Women and Children, our Ships and goods taken and sunke, and the Owners stript naked, and more inhumanely used at the Commandement of abused Authority, by the Subjects of our owne King, then by Turkes and Infidels, and great Armies prepared against us with a terrible Commis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to subdue and destroy our <hi>selves,</hi> our Religion, Liberties, Lawes and all.</p>
            <p>In this extremity for us to send new Commissioners and Petitions were against sence and experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, those that governe the Kings Counsels, being farre from any inclination or intention to satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the just desires and grievances of the Subjects, as they have made manifest by breaking up of the Parliament in both Kingdomes (though we know them to be often countervoted by many of that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Board, more candid and peaceably minded) To sit still in senselessnesse and security, wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for our owne destruction at the discretion of our mercilesse enemies (which were it not at this time joyned with the cause of <hi>God,</hi> would move us the lesse) is not onely against Religion but Nature, teaching and commanding us to study our owne preservation To endure continuall <hi>threatenings,</hi> and so great <hi>hostility</hi> and <hi>invasion</hi> from yeare to yeare, which is the professed policy of our enemies is impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, and when we have examined our owne strength, more then we are able to beare: We have therefore after much agitation and debating with and amongst our selves, resolved to have our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:158230:4"/> which have beene canvased by so many, and are brought to some point of <hi>determination</hi> in our owne <hi>Parliament,</hi> to be better knowne to the Kings Majesty, and the world, and especially to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> that against all false and artificiall Relations they being nakedly seene to bee what they are, we may obtaine a better grounded and more durable <hi>peace</hi> for the enjoying of our own Religion and Lawes, and as we desire the unworthy Authours of our troubles, who have come out from our selves to be tryed at home, and <hi>Iustice</hi> to be done upon them, according to our owne Laws, so shall we presse no further processe against <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the rest of those pernicious Counsellours in <hi>England</hi> the Authours of all the miseries of both Kingdomes, then what their owne Parliament shall discerne to be their just deserving.</p>
            <p>When we looke backe upon this worke of <hi>Reformation</hi> from the beginning, and perceive the impressions of the providence of God in it, we are forced in the midst of all our <hi>difficulties</hi> and <hi>distresses</hi> to blesse God for his fatherly care and free love to his Church and Kingdome, and to take courage and spirit to proceed in <hi>patience</hi> and <hi>perseverance</hi> whither he shall goe before us, and lead us on. When the Prelates were growne by their rents and lordly dignities, by their power over all sorts of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties Subjects, Ministers and others, by their places in Parliament, Councell, Colledge of Justice, Exchequer and High-commission, to an absolute Dominion, and Greatnesse, and setting the one foot upon the Church, and the other upon the State, were become intollerably insolent, even then did the worke begin, and this was the <hi>Lords opportunity.</hi> The beginnings were small, and promised no great thing, but have been so seconded and continually followed by <hi>divine providence,</hi> pressing us from step to step, that the necessity was invincible and could not be resisted. It cannot be expressed what mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions filled the heart, what <hi>teares</hi> were powred forth from the <hi>eyes,</hi> and what <hi>cryes</hi> came from the <hi>mouthes</hi> of many thousands in this Land at that time, from the sence of the Love and Power of <hi>God,</hi> raysing them as from the <hi>dead,</hi> and giving them hopes after so great a deluge and vastation to see a new world, wherein Religion and Righteousnesse should dwell. When we were many times at a pause, and knew not well what to doe, the <hi>feares,</hi> the <hi>furies,</hi> the <hi>peevishnesse</hi> and the plots of our dementat adversaries opened a way unto us, and taught us how to proceed, and what they devised to ruine us served most against themselves, and for raysing and promoting the worke, <hi>O providence to be adored!</hi> Although neither Counsell nor Session, nor any other judicature hath bin all this time sitting, and there have bin meetings of many thousands at some times, yet have they bin kept without <hi>tumult</hi> or <hi>trouble,</hi> and without excesse or ryot in better order and greater quietnesse, then in the most <hi>peaceable times</hi> have bin found in this Land.</p>
            <p>When we were content at the <hi>pacification</hi> to lay downe Armes, and with great losse to live at home in <hi>peace,</hi> our wicked enemies have been like the troubled Sea when it cannot rest, whose <hi>waters cast up mire and dirt,</hi> and will have us to doe that which it seemes the <hi>Lord</hi> hath decreed against them. The purity of our <hi>intentions</hi> farre from base and earthly respects, the bent and inclination of our <hi>hearts</hi> in the midst of many dangers, the sitting of instruments, not onely with a desire and disposition, but with spirit and abilities to overcome <hi>opposition,</hi> and the constant peace of <hi>heart</hi> accompanying us in our wayes, which beareth us out against all accusations and aspersions, are to us strong grounds of as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surance that God hath <hi>accepted</hi> our <hi>work,</hi> and will not leave us: we know the Lord may use even wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked men in his <hi>service,</hi> and may fill their sailes with a faire gale of <hi>abilities,</hi> and carry them on with a strong hand, which should make us to search our hearts more narrowly. But as this ought not to discourage his owne <hi>faithfull servants,</hi> who out of <hi>love</hi> to his Name intend his <hi>honour,</hi> walke in his <hi>wayes,</hi> find his <hi>peace comforting them,</hi> his <hi>providence directing them,</hi> and his <hi>presence blessing them</hi> in their affaires. So can it not be any just ground of quarrelling against the worke of God. Yet all these our incouragements which have upholden our <hi>hearts</hi> in the midst of many <hi>troubles,</hi> could not make our entry into <hi>England</hi> warrantable, if our peace (which we earnestly seeke and follow after) could be found at home or elsewhere. Where it is to be found we must seeke after it, and no sooner shall we finde it clearly secured to us, but by laying downe our Armes, and by the evidences of our peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able disposition, we shall make it manifest to the world, and especially to the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> that we are seeking nothing els but <hi>peace,</hi> and that our taking up of Armes was not for invasion but for defence. No man needeth to plead by <hi>positive Law</hi> for <hi>necessity.</hi> It is written in every mans <hi>heart</hi> by <hi>nature,</hi> and in all actions we find men have received it by <hi>practise, that necessity is a Soveraignty.</hi> A Law above all Lawes and subject to no Law, and therfore is said to have no Law. Where <hi>necessity commandeth,</hi> the Laws of <hi>nature</hi> and Nations give their <hi>consent,</hi> and all <hi>positive Lawes</hi> are <hi>silent</hi> and give place. This Law hath place, sometimes to excuse, sometimes to <hi>extenuate,</hi> and sometimes to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:158230:4"/>
               <hi>justifie</hi> and <hi>warrant actions</hi> otherwise questionable: and no <hi>greater necessity</hi> can be then the <hi>preserva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Religion,</hi> which is the <hi>soule</hi> of the <hi>Country,</hi> which is the <hi>body</hi> of our lives, who are the <hi>mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> and of the <hi>honour</hi> of our King who is the <hi>Head.</hi> All these at this time are in a common hazard, and to preserve and secure all, we know no other way under the Sun (and if any be so wise as to know it, we desire to heare it, and shall be ready to follow it) but to take order with our common enemies where they may be found, and to seeke our assurance where it may be given. The question is not whither we shall content our selves with our owne <hi>poverty,</hi> or <hi>enrich</hi> our selves in <hi>England?</hi> that que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion is impious and absurd. Neither is the question, whither we shall <hi>defend our se<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> or <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade</hi> our <hi>neighbours</hi> and dearest Brethren? this also were unchristian and unreasonable. But this is the question, whither it be <hi>wisedome</hi> and <hi>piety</hi> to keepe our selves within the borders till our <hi>throats</hi> be cut, and our <hi>Religion,</hi> Lawes and Country <hi>destroyed?</hi> Or, shall we be stirre our selves, and seeke our <hi>safeguard, peace</hi> and <hi>liberty</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> whither we shall <hi>doe</hi> or <hi>dye,</hi> whither we shall <hi>goe</hi> and <hi>live,</hi> or <hi>abide</hi> and <hi>perish?</hi> Or more largely to expresse all, whither we who are not a few <hi>private persons,</hi> but a whole Kingdom, shall lye under the burthen of so many <hi>accusations,</hi> as sencely in the worst times have been charged against Christians, receive the Service Book, &amp; the whole body of Popery, imbrace the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates and their abjured Hierarchy, renounce our solemn Oath and Covenant, so many times sworn by us, loose all our labour and pains in this cause, and forget our former slavery and wonted desires of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion at the dearest rate, tickle the minds of our enemies with joy, and strengthen their hands vvith vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and fill the hearts of our friends with <hi>sorrow,</hi> and their faces with <hi>shame,</hi> because of us: <hi>desert</hi> and <hi>dishonour</hi> the Son of God, whose cause we have undertaken, whose <hi>banner</hi> we have <hi>displayed,</hi> and whose <hi>truth</hi> and power hath bin this time past more comfortable to us, then all the <hi>peace and prospe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of the world could have rendered, and draw upon our selves all the <hi>judgements</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath executed upon Apostates since the beginning, and shall we fold our hands and wait for the perfect slavery of our selves and our Posterity, in our <hi>soules, bodies,</hi> and <hi>estates,</hi> and (which is all one) foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lishly to stand to our <hi>defence</hi> where we know it is in possible? Or shall we seeke our reliefe in follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the calling of God (for our <hi>necessity</hi> can be interpreted no lesse) and entring by the doore, which his <hi>providence</hi> hath opened unto us, when all wayes are stopped beside.</p>
            <p>Our enemies at first did shroude themselves so farre under the Kings Authority, that they behoved to stand or fall together, and that to censure them was treason against the King Now we have shewen that a Kings Crowne is not tyed to a Prelates Mitre, and that the one may be cast unto the ground, and the other have a greater lustre and glory then before. Now they take themselves to another star<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hole, and would have men to thinke, that to come into <hi>England</hi> against them is to come against <hi>England,</hi> and to pursue them although legally, is to invade the Kingdome where they live, as if the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away of an <hi>Excrescence</hi> or the curing of <hi>an Impost hume</hi> were the killing of the body. Let them se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure themselves under the shelter of their owne <hi>phantasies,</hi> but we are not so undiscerning, as like mad men to run furiously upon such as we first meet with and come in our way: For although it cannot be denied but the wrongs done to us, as the breaking of the late <hi>peace,</hi> crying us downe as <hi>Rebels and Traitours,</hi> the taking of our Ships and goods, the imprisoning of our <hi>Commissioners,</hi> the Acts of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stility</hi> done by the <hi>English</hi> in our Castles: had they bin done by the State or Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> there might have bin just causes of a Nationall quarrelling, yet seeing the Kingdome of <hi>England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veened in <hi>Parliament</hi> have refused to contribute any supply against us, have shewen themselves to bee prest with <hi>grievances</hi> like unto ours, and have earnestly pleaded for redresse and remedy, and a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration made that his Majesty out of <hi>Parliament</hi> will redresse them, which might be a cure for the grievances of particular Subjects: But Nationall grievances require the hand of the <hi>Parliament</hi> for their cure, for preventing wherof the <hi>Parliament</hi> was broken up and dissolved. Neither doe wee quarrell with the Kingdome for the injuries which we sustaine, but our quarrell is only with particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar men, the enemies of both Nations: nor can they quarrell with us, for taking order with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent Faction of Papists and Prelates, the Authours of so many woes to both Nations.</p>
            <p>Let all who love Religion and their <hi>liberty</hi> joyne against the common enemies, and let them be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cursed that shall not seeke the preservation of their Neighbour Nation, both in Religion and Lawes, as their owne, as knowing that the ruine of one will prove the ruine of both. And knowing well (as having from their owne Councels discovered it) that the ruine of both vvas intended, and that it vvas ever their plot and purpose, that if they could not ingage our dearest Brethren and Neighbour-Nation in a Warre for our <hi>destruction;</hi> then to give us some ill assured <hi>peace,</hi> vvhich might bind our hands and hold us quiet, untill the yoake of bondage were more heavily and unremoveably laid upon
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:158230:5"/> our Brethren of <hi>England</hi> by the helpe of such an Army as was pretended to be gathered against as, roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the godly people and active spirits of that Nation, and all those who as good Patriots stand well affected to Religion, and their just liberties, and might be suspected would dare stirre for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and maintenance of either, and thereafter easily find ground to breake againe with us, when they were once assured that vve vvere like to stand alone: And all the benefit of our <hi>peace</hi> should be to be last <hi>destroyed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we attest the God of Heaven, that those and no other are our <hi>intentions,</hi> so upon the same greatest attestation doe vve declare that for archieving those ends, vve shall neither spare out <hi>paines, fortunes</hi> nor <hi>lives</hi> vvhich vve know cannot be more profitably and honourably spent. That we shall not take from our Friends and Brethren from a threed even to a shoe-latchet, but for our owne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and the just payment: That vve come amongst them as their Friends and Brethren, very sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible of their by-past sufferings and present dangers both in Religion and Liberties, and most willing to doe them all the good vve can, like as vve certainly expect that they (from the like sence of our hard condition and intollerable distresse which hath forced us to come from our owne Country) will joyne and concurre vvith us in the most just and noble vvayes for obtaining their and our most just de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires. And vvhen our owne <hi>moneys</hi> and meanes are spent, vve shall crave nothing but upon sufficient surety of payment how soone possibly it can be made, what is necessary for the intertainment of our Army, vvhich vve are assured so many as love Religion and the <hi>peace</hi> of both Kingdomes vvill wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly offer, as that vvhich they know vve cannot vvant, and in their vvise fore-sight vvill provide the vvay to furnish necessaries, and to receive the <hi>surety.</hi> This course being kept by both sides, vvill neither harme our Brethren (for they shall be satisfied to the last <hi>farthing</hi>) nor our selves, vvho look for a recompence from the <hi>rich providence of God,</hi> for vvhose sake vve have hazarded the losse of all things.</p>
            <p>The escapes of some Souldiers (if any shall happen) we trust shall not be imputed to us, vvho shall labour by all meanes to prevent them more carefully, and punish them more severely then if done to our selves and in our owne Country. Our professed enemies the Papists, Prelates vvith their Adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and the receivers of their <hi>goods and geir;</hi> vve conceive vvill be more provident then to refuse us necessary <hi>sustentation,</hi> vvhen they remember vvhat Councell vvas given by them for declaring all our possessions to be <hi>forfeited</hi> and to be disposed of to them, as well deserving Subjects.</p>
            <p>We shall demand nothing of the Kings Majesty but the setling and securing of the true <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>liberties</hi> of this Kingdome according to the Constitutions and Acts of the late Assemblies and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and vvhat a just Prince oweth by the Laws of God and the Country to his grieved Subjects, comming before him vvith the r <hi>humble desires and supplications.</hi> Our abode in <hi>England</hi> shall be no longer time then in their Parliament, our just <hi>grievances and complaints</hi> may be heard and redressed, su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fficient <hi>assurance</hi> given for the legall tryall and <hi>punishment</hi> of the Authors of their and our evils; and for reforming and enjoying their and our <hi>Religion and Liberties</hi> in <hi>peace</hi> against the machinations of Romish contrivance acted by their degenerate <hi>Country men.</hi> Our returning thereafter shall be vvith expedition in a peaceable and orderly vvay farre from all <hi>molestation,</hi> and vve trust the effect shall be against Papists, the extirpation of Popery, against Prelates, the Reformation of the Kirk, against A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theists, the flourishing of the Gospell, and against Traitours and Fire-brands; a perfect and durable <hi>Vnion and Love</hi> betvveen the tvvo Kingdomes; vvhich he grant vvho knovveth our <hi>intentions and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires,</hi> and is able to bring them to passe. And if any more be required God vvill reveale it and got be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore both Nations, and if God goe before us vvho vvill not follovv or refuse to put their <hi>necks to the worke of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>